Guide to the Ludlow Seguine Bull Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Ludlow Seguine Bull papers
1922-1952
MS 111
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
4.5
(11 boxes)
Correspondence, writings, memoranda, minutes, legal and financial papers and printed matter relating to Bull's career as an Egyptologist and to his social, philanthropic and financial activities.His professional papers concern his curatorship of the Egyptian collections at the Metropolitan Museum of Art in New York City and at Yale University. As a resident of Litchfield, Connecticut, Bull was active in supporting various community institutions. These activities are documented by minutes and memoranda on the work of these institutions as well as financial statements on Bull's support. Also in the papers are documents on the history of the house known as "The Lindens" in Litchfield. The writings include a typescript of his Ph.D. thesis (1922) on religious texts of the Middle Kingdom and drafts for his book, The Rhind Mathematical Papyrus, published 1927-1929.
Bull, Ludlow Seguine, 1886-1954
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of the Ludlow S. Bull estate, 1954.
Scope and Contents
The papers of Luldow Seguine Bull consist of correspondence, writings, memoranda and minutes, legal and financial papers, and printed matter, 1922-1952, dealing both with Bull's career as an Egyptologist and with his social, philanthropic, and financial activities. In the current arrangement of the papers Bull's original folder headings have been retained wherever possible. The papers are divided into four series: PROFESSIONAL CORRESPONDENCE, GENERAL CORRESPONDENCE, LEGAL AND FINANCIAL PAPERS, and WRITINGS. PROFESSIONAL CORRESPONDENCE contains letters, memoranda, reports, minutes, printed matter, and occasional photographs relating to Bull's curator-ship at the Metropolitan Museum of Art in New York and at Yale University, his membership in professional societies, his teaching responsibilities at Yale and elsewhere, and his activities as a consultant on ancient artefacts. There is correspondence concerning his co-editorship of The Rhind Mathematical Papyrus(published in two volumes, 1927-1929) with A.B. Chace, H.P. Manning, R.C. Archibald, and S.R.K. Glanville. There are also minutes and correspondence of the,Metropolitan Museum Studies editorial board, of which Bull was secretary, and correspondence with Mrs. John S. Morrin concerning the loan of her collection of Egyptian and Eastern Mediterranean glass to Yale. The Yale University correspondence is largely routine, dealing with curricula, classes, and business of the Babylonian Collection, the Peabody Museum, the School of Fine Arts, and various academic departments. Among the correspondents are Theodore Sizer and George Parmly Day.
GENERAL CORRESPONDENCE reflects Bull's philanthropic and social interests. He was on the board of trustees of Pomfret School and of Litchfield's Spring High School, and included with the correspondence are minutes, financial papers, and architects' plans for additions to Pomfret School. Bull was active in church affairs in both Litchfield and New York, and was a member of the board of the Youth Consultation Service of the Diocese of New York, a social welfare organization designed to help young people with education and employment. Included among the papers are minutes, and memoranda on social work. Also in this series are correspondence and printed matter from several of Bull's clubs, including the Yale Club and the Class of 1907 Dinner Club.
LEGAL AND FINANCIAL PAPERS contains primarily papers relating to houses and other properties owned by Bull. Among these papers are correspondence, inventories, deeds and other legal papers, receipts, bills, and other financial papers. Included with the papers about "The Lindens" in Litchfield is correspondence about the history of the house and of Litchfield in general, and about works of art kept in the house. Also in this series are receipts not related to Bull's property. They are largely acknowledgments of charitable contributions.
WRITINGS contains a typescript of Bull's Ph.D. thesis, and partial typescripts, notes, and galley proofs for The Rhind Mathematical Papyrus. There are also two notebooks on Egyptian topics.
Conditions Governing Access
The collection is open for research.
Egyptology; Public welfare; Connecticut; Litchfield (Conn.); Middle East; Archaeologists; Bull, Ludlow Seguine, 1886-1954; Metropolitan Museum of Art (New York, N.Y.); Yale University -- Officals and employees; Yale University -- Students; Yale University. Art Gallery
- PROFESSIONAL CORRESPONDENCE, 1923-1947, undated; Series I; 1.75' (4 boxes)
  - American Schools of Oriental Research (Robert M. Engberg, Secretary), 1939-1940 (Box 1, Folder 1-5)
  - Metropolitan Museum of Art
    - Department of Egyptian Art, 1924-1946, undated (Box 1, Folder 6-21)
    - Employees' Association, 1926-1942 (Box 1, Folder 22-27)
  - Metropolitan Museum Studies, 1927-1935 (Box 2, Folder 28-29)
  - Morrin, Caroline L. (Mrs. John S.), 1936-1943 (Box 2, Folder 30-31)
  - The Rhind Mathematical Papyrus, 1925-1928 (Box 2, Folder 32-51)
  - Yale University, 1924-1939 (Box 3, Folder 52-82)
  - Yale University, 1940-1947 (Box 4, Folder 83-92)
  - Miscellaneous, 1923-1946, undated (Box 4, Folder 93-105)
- GENERAL CORRESPONDENCE, 1924-1952, undated; Series II; 1.75' (5 boxes)
  - Marshepaug Forest Club (Litchfield, Ct.), 1929-1949 (Box 5, Folder 1-5)
  - Pomfret School (Pomfret, Ct.)
    - Letters, 1935-1943 September (Box 5, Folder 6-27)
    - Letters, 1943 October-1951 (Box 6, Folder 28-58)
    - Address by L.S.B. on Pomfret Prize Day, 1944 June 3 (Box 6, Folder 59)
  - St. James' Church (New York, N.Y.), 1931-1948, n.d (Box 7, Folder 60-64)
  - St. Michael's Church (Litchfield, Ct.), 1935-1947 (Box 7, Folder 65-68)
  - Spring High School (Litchfield, Ct.), 1935-1939 (Box 7, Folder 69-70)
  - The University Club (New York, N.Y.), 1938-1948 (Box 7, Folder 71-83)
  - Yale Club and Class of 1907 Dinner Club, 1948-1952 (Box 8, Folder 84-91)
  - Youth Consultation Service, Episcopal Diocese of New York, 1940-1951 (Box 8, Folder 92-114)
  - Miscellaneous, 1924-1950, n.d (Box 9, Folder 115-129)
- LEGAL AND FINANCIAL PAPERS, 1925-1948; Series III; 7.5"(2 boxes)
  - Papers concerning property
    - "The Lindens" (Litchfield, Ct.), 1931-1939 (Box 9, Folder 1-9)
    - "The Lindens" (Litchfield, Ct.), 1940-1948, undated (Box 10, Folder 10-22)
    - North Street house (Litchfield, Ct.), 1925-1947 (Box 10, Folder 23-28)
    - "Steepways" (Point-au-pic, Quebec, Canada), 1936-1938 (Box 10, Folder 29)
    - Waterbury house (Waterbury, Ct.), 1936-1937 (Box 10, Folder 30-31)
  - Receipts, 1928-1946 (Box 10, Folder 32-35)
- WRITINGS, 1922-1929, undated; Series IV; 5" (1 box)
  - "The Religious Texts from an Egyptian Coffin of the Middle Kingdom," Ph.D. thesis, University of Chicago
    - Typescript and notes, 1922 (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Abstract, 1922 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - The Rhind Mathematical Papyrus
    - "Introduction", 1927-1929 (Box 11, Folder 3-4)
    - "Introduction, revision", [1927-1929] (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - "Free Translation and Commentary," Chap. I, [1927-1929] (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - "Translation and notes," Chap. I, [1927-1929] (Box 11, Folder 7-8)
    - Notes, [1927-1929] (Box 11, Folder 9)
    - Galley proofs, [1927-1929] (Box 11, Folder 10)
    - Copies of plates, [1927-1929] (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - Notebooks
    - "Pyramid Texts, Vol. II, Translation and Notes", undated (Box 11, Folder 12)
    - Re: Egyptian artifacts, undated (Box 11, Folder 13)